<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The most notable and excellent discourse of the Christian philosopher Athenagoras, as touching the resurrection of the dead, translated out of Greeke into Latine by Peter Nannius, and out of Latin into English by R. Porder. A treatise, very necessarie and profitable for this our laste ruinous age of the vvorlde, in the vvhiche are such svvarmes of atheistes and epicures, vvhose pestilent infection is more to be feared then papistrie. Therefore vvorthy the consideracion of al men, as vvel for ouerthrovv of their pernicious errours, as staying the faith and conscience of the vveake and vnlearned.</title>
            <title>De resurrectione. English</title>
            <author>Athenagoras, 2nd cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1573</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22442</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 886</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114473</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849698</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849698</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14860</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22442)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14860)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 635:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The most notable and excellent discourse of the Christian philosopher Athenagoras, as touching the resurrection of the dead, translated out of Greeke into Latine by Peter Nannius, and out of Latin into English by R. Porder. A treatise, very necessarie and profitable for this our laste ruinous age of the vvorlde, in the vvhiche are such svvarmes of atheistes and epicures, vvhose pestilent infection is more to be feared then papistrie. Therefore vvorthy the consideracion of al men, as vvel for ouerthrovv of their pernicious errours, as staying the faith and conscience of the vveake and vnlearned.</title>
                  <title>De resurrectione. English</title>
                  <author>Athenagoras, 2nd cent.</author>
                  <author>Porder, Richard, d. 1547.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[78] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Pavvles Churchyarde, by VV. VVilliamson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1573.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by Richard Porder, of: Athenagoras. Peri anastaseōs nekrōn.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Athenagoras of the resur. of the deade.</note>
                  <note>Final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: pi¹ A-H⁴ I⁶.</note>
                  <note>Some pages stained; I5, final printed leaf, cropped at foot.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Resurrection --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14860:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14860:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ The moſt notable and excellent diſcourſe of the Christian Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher Athenagoras, as touching the Reſurrection of the dead, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated out of Greeke into La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine by <hi>Peter Nannius,</hi> and out of Latin in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to English by R. Porder.</p>
            <p>A TREATISE. VERY NECES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie and profitable for this our laſte ruinous age of the vvorlde, in the vvhiche are ſuche ſvvarmes of Atheiſtes and Epicures, vvhoſe peſtilent infection is more to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red then papiſtrie. Therefore vvorthy the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideracion of al men, as vvel for ouerthrovv of their pernicious errours, as ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the faith and conſcience of the vveake and vnlearned.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London in Pavvles Churchyarde, by VV. VVilliamſon.</p>
            <p>Anno. 1573.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14860:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14860:2"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>To the right worſhipfull,</hi> his ſinguler good friend M. VVilliam Fleetevvood Eſquier, Recorder of the moſt honorable Citie of London, his vvel vviller Richard Porder vvish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth felicitie in Chriſt Ieſu.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is true (righte</hi> worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſir) vvhich the auctor of this vvorke at the very firſt entrye thereof doth aledge, that ſome errour doth as it vvere cleaue to euery treatiſe or disputacion, for <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> contendeth that <hi>mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dus eſt ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternus,</hi> The <hi>Stoickes</hi> haue aſſigned tvvo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginninges of all thinges, to vveete, <hi>Deus, &amp; materia: Democritus</hi> and <hi>Epicurus</hi> ſay, the vvorlde is compoſed <hi>ex atomis temere &amp; ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu concurrentibus,</hi> that is: of litle motes fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together in the ayre, and cleuing one to an other, and ſo increaſing this great maſſi lu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe, or earthy globe of the vvorlde. <hi>Thales</hi> ſaith, vvater vvas the broode mother and beginning of all thinges. &amp;c. And other acknovvledged this vvorlde to haue a beginning, and God to be the cauſe of that beginning, and by their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent ſtudies and vviſedome, haue founde out of vvhat diuers elementes mankinde vvas compoſed: Yea further by their great knovv
<pb facs="tcp:14860:3"/>
ledge in many mightie vvorckes of God, but specially in the creation of man, they confeſſed God to be perfectly vviſe, perfectly iuste, and <hi>ſummum bonum,</hi> out of vvhich reaſonable knovvledg (naturaly graffed in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſeemeth) the auctour of this treatiſe toke his ground to prooue the reſurrection of the dead by reaſon. Firſt admonishing all thoſe that doubt or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue not this doctrine, to examine effectualy by reaſon the cauſe of their vnbelefe or doubting, for he affirmeth truly, that to admit doubtes, or incredulitie vvithout due examination in reaſon vvhy, is the part of the prodigall as he calleth them, that is, of ſuche as spende their vvittes vvaſt fully and careleſlye, vvithoute reaſon or iudgement: and as there vvere ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye errours about the beginning of thinges, ſo not a fevve errors (touching the repairing of thoſe thinges, vvhich God made to be resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red after their diſſolution) vvere the cauſe of this mans vvriting. For <hi>Epicures</hi> &amp; the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces</hi> flatly denyed the reſurrection, As <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danapalus</hi> last king of Syria declareth in an Epitaphe, vvhich he made for him ſelfe a litle before he leaped headlong into the fire, vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he vvas brent as <hi>Strabo</hi> noteth.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>Cum te mortalem noris, preſentibus exple</l>
               <l>Delitiis animum, poſt mortem nulla voluptas</l>
               <l>Nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ego ſum puluis, qui nuper tanta tenebam</l>
               <l>Haec habeo quae edi, quae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> exaturata libido</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14860:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Hauſit: at illa manent multa &amp; preclara relicta</l>
               <l>Hoc ſapiens vitae mortalibus eſt documentum</l>
            </q>
            <p>That is, for aſmuch, as thou knovveſt thy ſelf to be mortall, glut thy deſire vvith preſente delights. After death there is no pleaſant ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, for ſee I am duſt, vvhich of late poſſeſſed ſo great honour &amp; ritches. Thoſe things onc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly J haue, vvhich I did eate: Yea vvhat gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye luſt hath deuoured, I holde in poſſeſſion: But all my golde, magnificient buyldinges, landes, ritches and honour left behinde mee remayne for other. Loe I am an example and vviſe leſſon for all mortall creatures to conſider. It greeued this <hi>Epicure</hi> that hee coulde not eate all the vvorld vvhile he liued: Alſo <hi>Philetus</hi> &amp; <hi>Hymineus</hi> ſaide, it should be spiritual. Some heahten hathbeleeued the ſoule onelye shoulde remayne for euer vvith the Gods. And other thought the ſoule should ſuruiue the body, and yet could not tell vvhat shoulde become of it, as <hi>Aelius Adrianus</hi> the <hi>Emperour,</hi> vvho deſperatly cryed in his ſickeneſſe,</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>Animula vagula blandula</l>
               <l>Que nunc abibis in loca?</l>
               <l>Nec vt ſoles, dabisiocos</l>
               <l>Hoſpes comeſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> corporis</l>
               <l>Pallidula, rigid a nudula.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Oh my litle ſvveete ſoule, vvhither vvilt thou novve departe avvaye from mee? For
<pb facs="tcp:14860:4"/>
thou being pale, nomme, and naked, shalt not henceforth enioye thy pleaſures as in times paſt, being a gheſt and companion of the body. Other thought that ſoule and body did perish together, and alſo shoulde riſe againe in the last day, of vvho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Euſebius,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Exorti ſunt autem alij quidam tum temporis in Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia. &amp;c.</hi> At that time there sprong up an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſecte in Arabia, vvhich helde an opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> contrary to the truth, vvhich ſayd that ſoules perished together vvith the bodies, and alſo shoulde riſe vvith the bodies in the last daye. Other affirmed that mens bodies should riſe, but not the ſelf ſame bodies, nor the ſame flesh. All vvhiche falſe opinions contraye to them ſelues, and repugnante to the Christian faith, as your vvorship heareth them dayly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>futed by aucthoritie of ſcriptures and examples in the ſame: ſo here you shall ſee the ſame ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throvven by force of reaſon: and vvhere ſome graunt God to be able, and yet doubt of his vvill, <hi>Athenagoras</hi> shevveth that the om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mpotencie, Iuſtice, vviſedome and vvill of God are ſo linked together by an inuiolable decree concerning this matter, that the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures</hi> may aſvvel deny that there is a God, as deny the reſurrestion of the dead, and laste iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And though ſome haue ſigned rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (as ſeemed to them) vvherfore they doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:14860:4"/>
of this matter, as the tranſmutacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of one ſubstaunce into an other by digestion (for ſo phiſitions define digeſtion) namely of mens bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies deuoured of beastes and birdes, and the ſame beaſtes and birdes deuoured by men. &amp;c. And ſo conclude an impoſſibilitie that men should riſe againe vvith their ovvne bodies. The aucthor doth phiſically make avvaye to looſe or vnknit thoſe doubts by theſe reaſons, that all ſuch meate as man and beast eateth, is not tourned into the ſubſtance of the eater, but onely that part vvhich is truely naturall for ſubſtanciall foode by order of creation or of nature. And that ſeeing the creator vvas able and did knovv hovv to compoſe bodies of ſundry ſeuered ſubstances, he alſo is able and could not be ignoraunt hovve to conſerue the integritie of the nature &amp; ſubſtances compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, though they might be diſſolued and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into hovv many ſo euer thouſand parts or places. Againſt the heathen he affirmeth that vvho ſo euer hath receaued the lavve, muſt be iuſtified or condempned, but it vvas not the ſoule onely, but ſoule and body, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſoule and body muſt be iustified or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, vvhich canot be vnleſſe the body riſe, <hi>ergo</hi> the dead muſt needes riſe againe. And further as it is abſurde to attribute the affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the body to the ſoule, ſo is it an vniust
<pb facs="tcp:14860:5"/>
thing to ſaye the ſoule shalbe iuſtified or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempned: but it is abſurde to ſaye the ſoule is a theefe, a hooremonger, or murtherer, for that vvay the ſoule offendeth by the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of the bodie, and therefore ſoule and bodie must needes come to iudgement, vvhich cannot be vnleſſe the dead riſe, and therefore the dead muſt needes riſe again. And though it may be ſaide theſe be but arguments proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and not neceſſaryly strong of them ſelues, to confirme or ſtablish the truth: yet are they of ſufficient force to shake doubtes and incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulitie in peeces, vvhich is the auctors pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in this treatiſe, and therefore I referre your vvorship to his argumentes, you shall finde him hard, &amp; no maruaile, for he vvrote in Greeke, vvhich tongue muche abhorreth our commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> phraſe. There vvas but one copie in <hi>Europe</hi> to be foundvvhen this vvas firſt tranſlated into latine, and therefore might be infected. And beſides this <hi>Athenagoras</hi> doth not only play the Philoſopher in matters phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophicall, but in the profoundeſt matter of Religion, ſo that your vvorship taking him in your hande, haue to deale aſmuche vvith a moſt cunning deuine, as vvith a moſte vviſe philoſopher, and in a matter of great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce: namely the reſurrection of the dead, vvheron the chiefeſt parte of our religion de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth
<pb facs="tcp:14860:5"/>
               <hi>M. Peter Nannius</hi> taught him to speake latine thirtie tvvo yeres ſince at the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſitie of <hi>Louane</hi> in <hi>Brabant,</hi> and novve I haue taught him to speake english in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, made him a free denizen, and broughte him acquainted vvith your vvorſhip, as vvith a man very meete for vviſedome, learning, &amp; aucthority, to giue in the behalfe of our vvhole citie honorable interteignement to ſo noble a straunger. And as I hartelye deſire you to accept my doinges as a token of thankefulnes (though farre from a iuſte recompence) for your manifolde friendshippe to mee ſundrye vvayes shevved: So I humbly beſeeche you to make him a free man of London, bring him acquaynted vvith the honorable Lorde Mayor, &amp; his right vvorshipful brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Aldermen, vvith liueries of all compaignies, and their yeomanries, for he vvas a vviſe Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tezen, a Religious deuine, a prudent philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, a great louer of Justice, &amp; a most faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Patrone to Christes Church, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in that more then thirteene hundred yeres ago, he vvrote an Apologie or defence in Greeke to <hi>Antonius</hi> &amp; <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modus</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, in the behalfe of the Chriſtians. No de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelishe Diagoras can race the vvalles of that Citie vvhere godly <hi>Athenagoras</hi> dvvelleth: All godleſſe <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> beaſtly <hi>Epicures,</hi> ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing
<pb facs="tcp:14860:6"/>
               <hi>Lucianiſts,</hi> mocking <hi>Machiaueliſts,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolting <hi>Iulianiſtes,</hi> Hipocrites and abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable vvorkers hovv ſoeuer they bleare mens eyes, are made afrayed by <hi>Athenagoras</hi> of that iuſt iudge, vvhich cannot be blinded, bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, out faced, nor intreated, before vvhome all must stande, having their deedes naked and bare to aunſvvere for them ſelues, and receaue ſentence of life or death eternallye. And thus fearing lest through vttering ouer many vvaste vvoords, I may be thought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther comberous then commendable, I beſeech the almightie preſerue your vvorship to his vvill and pleaſure.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>At Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don <date>this 10. of October. Anno. 1573.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By yours to his poore power,</hi>
Richard Porder.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14860:6"/>
            <head>¶ ATHENAGORAS, A Chriſtian Philoſopher of Athenes, of the Reſurrection of the dead.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome errour doeth, as it were, growe, &amp; very neerly cleaue vnto euerye deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and treatiſe, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che dependeth &amp; is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the trueth of theſe thinges.</p>
            <p>But it procéedeth not of any principle, and naturall inclination of the thinges, nor of the cauſes of their ſubſtaunce, but by the labour, and means, of them, which do eſtéeme and haue in great honour coi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeyt ſéede, to corrupt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trueth withall.</p>
            <p>That this thing is true, you may eaſily gather. Firſt by the earneſt ſtudy of aur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient writers, which beſtowed their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour vpon this matter, in that they do diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, both from them whiche were long time before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as alſo from thoſe which liued in their time. But eſpecially you maye gather it by the variety of opinions which were amongſt them.</p>
            <p>For theſe men dyd let no trueth paſſe without ſome deprauing, no not the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledge, not the working, of God, nor many other things, which do in order followe theſe. No not ſo much as
<pb facs="tcp:14860:7"/>
ſpeache which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> painter of al godlines.</p>
            <p>For ſome of them do vtterly diſpayre to atteyne the trueth of ſuch things, other ſome do writhe away themſelues to that which ſéemeth to them beſt, and other do much doubte in thinges manifeſt.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I thinke, that he, whiche mindeth to diſpute of theſe matters, had néede to vſe twoo maner of treatiſes, the one to make defence for the trueth. The other to try which is the trueth. The firſt I thinke muſt be vſed againſt thoſe, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che be doubtfull, and harde of beléefe, the ſeconde to them, that wiſhe well, and bée fauourers of the trueth.</p>
            <p>Wherefore it behooueth them, which do minde to boolte, and to ſearch the nature of theſe matters, to marke diligentlye, what preſente commodity requireth, and therby to directe their diſcourſe, and fitly apply the order of things to neceſſitie, that whils they do place thoſe things, which be firſt according to order in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt place, they do not againſt that, which is ſeemely, and forſake the reſpecte of neceſſitie, care, and or congruitye.</p>
            <p>For like as vnto a demonſtration, &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall conſequence, thoſe thinges, whiche do entreate of the matter, are before thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:14860:7"/>
which are ſpoken in defence of it: ſo when wée haue reſpect to profite, thoſe thinges, which are in defence of the matter, are to be ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled before thoſe, which do diſcourſe of the matter.</p>
            <p>For like as the huſbandman can not conueniently ſowe his domeſticall ſéede, vnleſſe his grounde bee purged from all wilde, and vnkindely matter, and ſuche things as may annoye good ſeede: neither the phiſicion miniſter any wholſome me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine to a ſicke bodye, vnleſſe he purge him from all his noyſome humours, or ſtay the affluence of exceſſiue corruption and filthineſſe: ſo can not he, whiche tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the trueth, ſpeaking of the trueth, perſwade any thing, as long as their abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the minds of men a certayne falſe opinion, which doth gainſaye the reaſons of the trueth.</p>
            <p>Wherevpon wée hauing a reſpect, and regarde vnto co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gruity, &amp; conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, haue prepoſed our treatiſe of the defence of the trueth, before it, that doth entreate therof.</p>
            <p>Whiche thing at this time and in this queſtion to do ſéemeth not vnprofitable, whileſt we haue before our eies that, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che neceſſitie requireth, eſpecially in that diſcourſe which handleth the reſurrection
<pb facs="tcp:14860:8"/>
of the dead.</p>
            <p>For in this matter wée finde ſome, that vtterly beleeue it not, other ſome that are very doubtfull, and of them, which admit, and aſſent to the principles, and grounds of this queſtion, ſome do yet neuertheleſſe wauer in an vncertayne, and inconſtant opinion, as muche as they, whiche be doubtfull, and, that is moſte abſurde, they do ſuffer this wauering of minde without any occaſion of doubting, which they can drawe from thinges them ſelues.</p>
            <p>For they can alledge no cauſe any thing likely, why they either doubt, or ſtagger.</p>
            <p>That this thing is true you may eaſily perceyue after this maner.</p>
            <p>For truelye all hardeneſſe of beléefe, doth procéede not raſhly of a vayne, &amp; light opinion, but for ſome vrgent cauſe, &amp; like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihoode well fortified.</p>
            <p>For then incredulitie hath a reaſonable excuſe, when the matter it ſelfe, whiche is not beléeued, conteyneth ſome thing, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is incredible.</p>
            <p>For not to beléeue thoſe thinges which haue no cauſe of doubting, is propre to ſuch men, as do not vſe any ſounde iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in ſearching out of the trueth.</p>
            <p>Therfore it behooueth them, whiche do
<pb facs="tcp:14860:8"/>
not beléeue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or do doubt of it, not to directe their opinions according to that, which without conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſéemeth to them probable, or acceptable to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall, and thoſe which liue in too muche riote: but in ſearching and conſidering y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trueth of this doctrine, either to aſcribe no cauſe therof to the creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of man, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is eaſie to be refuted, or elſe to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute all things created to God the aucthor of all, and therby to prooue that the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in no caſe is to be beléeued.</p>
            <p>And they may do this, if either they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that God lacketh will, or wanteth power to reſtore to life a dead and diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued body, ſo that he make it ſounde, and ioyne it together, to renewe the forme of the olde man. Which thing if they can not prooue, let them leaue of their wicked vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beléefe, and deteſtable blaſphemie.</p>
            <p>But it ſhall appeare by thoſe thinges, that follow, that they ſay falſely, whether they alledge, that God can not, or that he will not. For lacke of power in anye man is therby perceyued, if either he know not what muſt be done, or if he know it, yet is ſo weake in ſtrength, that he can not well accompliſh the ſame.</p>
            <p>For he which knoweth not what muſt
<pb facs="tcp:14860:9"/>
be done, can neither take in hande, nor yet bring to paſſe anye thing at all, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of thoſe thinges, whiche he hath no knowledge of.</p>
            <p>But he that knoweth what is to bée done, and howe, and by what meanes it maye be finiſhed, but yet hath either no ſtrength at all, or elſe not ſufficient to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh the matter, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which he well vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth: he, if he be wiſe, &amp; wil looke vpon his owne abilitye, either will not take it in hand vnaduiſedly, or ſhalbe diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of the ende of his worke.</p>
            <p>But it is impoſſible, that God ſhould be ignoraunt in any point, or parcell of the bodyes, which be appointed for the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
            <p>For it is not poſſible, that it ſhoulde bée hidde from him, whether euery one of the corrupted members bee gone, and what putrified, things the partes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> elements haue receyued into them, &amp; haue admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into like nature, although amongeſt men, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is powred again into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall nature of the eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts doth ſéeme altogether inſeperable, &amp; indeprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſible.</p>
            <p>For to him, which before that any thing was created, was not ignorant of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the elementes, before they were,
<pb facs="tcp:14860:9"/>
where of bodies do take their beginning, neither were the parts of the elementes vnknowen, out of the which he was min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to gather that, which pleaſed him for the conſtitution of mans bodye, it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt enough, that he would not be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt, whether euery thing might departe which he tooke to make perfect his worke withal, when the compoſed maſſes are to be ſundered, and ſeuered.</p>
            <p>For as touching the order of our affay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and the iudgement of other our buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, it is a greater matter to foreknow thoſe thinges, whiche are not, yet before they come to paſſe: but as touching the maieſtie, &amp; wiſedome of God, both theſe are naturall &amp; like eaſie, both to foreknow thoſe thinges, which are not yet created, &amp; alſo to diſcerne thoſe things, which be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued.</p>
            <p>And truely euen the creation of bodyes doth well declare, that God hath power ſufficient to reſtore dead bodyes.</p>
            <p>For if he made bodies, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as yet they were not, and brought foorth the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of them, whence they had their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning: he can alſo repayre the ſame by what meane ſoeuer they were diſſolued, with the like caſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14860:10"/>
Neither here ſhall this reaſon fayle, whether they draw y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning of things from the matter, and ſtuffe of them, or frame bodies of the elementes, as the firſte principles of all thinges, or of their ſéede in procreation.</p>
            <p>For in whoſe power it is to tranſforme matter, which in the beginning was with out forme, and to adorne it with many, and diuerſe countenaunces, which before had no ſhape, and to gather together the partes of the elementes, and to diuide in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to manye parts the ſéede, which was one, and vniforme, and to garniſh that with ioynts which before was without ioynts, and to geue life to a thing without life: he alſo is able to vnite together that, which is ſcattered abroad, &amp; raiſe vp that, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che lyeth, and make that aliue, whiche is dead, and chaunge that, whiche was cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, into incorruption.</p>
            <p>The ſame workeman alſo, can by his power, and wiſedome, when a bodye is is toarne in péeces by a multitude of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe beaſtes (howe many ſo euer do vſe to ſet vpon ſuch bodies, &amp; therby fill their paunches) ſeperate it from them, and ioyne it again to his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, and partes, whether they went into one beaſt, or mo,
<pb facs="tcp:14860:10"/>
or whether they went into diuers, one after another ſucceſſiuelye, or whether with them being conſumed, they do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourne againe to their firſt beginninges, as by naturall putrefaction thinges are accuſtomed to do.</p>
            <p>This thing truely, doth ſéeme to haue greatlye troubled men of excellent lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which thought the doubting of the common people (I know not vpon what occaſion) to be weightie, &amp; of great force.</p>
            <p>They ſaye that manie bodies in ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke by ſea, and in riuers, haue béene meate to fiſhes, and that bodyes, whiche were ſlayne in warre, or vpon ſome other ſharpe occaſion, &amp; other circumſtances of things, when they could not be buried, were a praye to euery beaſt, as eche firſt could méete therewith.</p>
            <p>Séeing therefore that theſe bodies bée deuoured in ſuch ſorte, and the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, and partes, wherof theſe bodies dyd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, be torne in péeces, and therefore by the nature of growing together be made the brawnes, ſinews, &amp; inyutes of beaſts, they ſay it is impoſſible, that they ſhould ſuffer any ſeparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or diuiſion one from an other.</p>
            <p>Beſides this they bring foorth another
<pb facs="tcp:14860:11"/>
thing, which is more harde, namely, that ſéeing thoſe beaſtes which be nouriſhed with the members of men be eaten as fit for mans meate, and therefore being put into mens bellyes, be vnited together with the bodye of them, which eate them: it followeth neceſſaryly ſay they, that the members of man, whiche tell before to theſe beaſtes, for their foode, do paſſe into other mens bodies ſéeing thoſe beaſtes whiche dyd deuoure the fleſhe of man, do tranſmit their ſubſtance into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brawnes of them, whiche receyue nouriſhment of thoſe beaſtes whom men were eaten.</p>
            <p>Then do they here vnto tragically ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aggerate, the limmes of Children cut of and eaten either in hunger, or madneſſe, and children denoured of their parentes, through the craft and deceyt of enemies, they adde moreouer the table of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Meads and the tragicall banket of Thieſtes, and what ſo euer miſchiefe hath béene com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, either amongſt the Gréecians, or among the Barbaria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vpon theſe groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des they inferre wel as they ſuppoſe, that there can be no reſurrection, ſéeing it can not be, that the ſame members ſhoulde riſe againe in diuerſe bodyes together. For either the firſt bodies can not conſiſt,
<pb facs="tcp:14860:11"/>
when the limmes are gone thether, where they make a furniture, or if they be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the firſt owner, the bodies of them, which followe, can not be perfit.</p>
            <p>Theſe men do ſéeme to me, firſt of all to be ignoraunt of the power, &amp; wiſedome of the creatour, &amp; gouernour of all things, which prepareth nouriſhinent fit, &amp; agrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to euery nature, and kinde of liuing thing, &amp; doth not ordeyne euery nature to concurre to the contemperature, and mixture of euerye naturall body, neither doth ſtagger, &amp; ſtay in ſeuering the parts of thinges growen together, and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth all thinges according to their proper nature, both to do, &amp; ſuffer, and ſometime contrariewiſe ſtoppeth them, &amp; doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueigh, &amp; take awaye, what he liſt, &amp; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he liſteth.</p>
            <p>Beſide this the ſame men ſéeme to me, not to knowe throughly, the ſtrength and nature, either of thinges, whiche do nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe, or of thoſe which are nouriſhed. Otherwiſe they would haue knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that not euery thing, whiche is powred from one in to another, is made foode fit, &amp; agrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thing, that taketh it.</p>
            <p>But that ſome thinges aſſoone as they be receyued into the bellye, do periſhe,
<pb facs="tcp:14860:12"/>
either by vomiting, or by excrement, or by auoyding, by ſome other meane, ſo that they endure not one litle while the firſt, and natural concoction, or any other mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with the things, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nouriſhe. As ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not euery thing, which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>coct, &amp; hath ſuffered the firſt alteration, is wholly ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with that, which nouriſheth the body, ſéeing that ſome thinges thereof be, as it were, expelled of the nouriſhing power &amp; faculty of man, by the belly, &amp; other ſome after the ſeconde chaunge, and alteration in the liuer, are auoyded and ſeuered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other thinges, which do excéede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of nouriſhing, &amp; the very chaunge it ſelfe, which is in the liuer, doth not wholly nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe, but ſtrayneth ſome of it vnto accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed ſuperfluities: ſo in like maner the liuer doth ſometime conuert that, which it did reteyne to nouriſhe the partes of the bodie with all, into ſome other thing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the nature of that, whiche bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth greateſt ſway, and doth moſt abound, which is accuſtomed either to deſtroy that which is next vnto it, or elſe to chaunge it into his owne nature.</p>
            <p>Séeing that there is therfore much na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall difference, in all liuing creatures, &amp; ſéeing that foode muſt by nature bée aptly
<pb facs="tcp:14860:12"/>
applyed to euery kinde of beaſt, and chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with the body, whiche is nouriſhed therwith, and ſéeing that in the meate of creatures there be thrée maners of puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyinges, and auoydinges therof, it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite that, that meate periſhe wholly, or be ſent whether it is accuſtomed, or be chaunged into ſome other thing, what ſoeuer is not couenable for the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; foode of any creature, as a thing, which can not be mingled, and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered therwith, and the force of the nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment of the creature muſt naturally agrée, and deſcende through naturall (as I may terme them) ſieues &amp; ſarches, and being throughlye purged by theſe natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall cleanſinges be made moſt pure, that it maye be adioyned to the body, the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che only (if you vſe the termes of things a right) you maye call nouriſhmente, as that, which hath caſt awaye all, which is not agréeable, but hurtfull to the conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the creature to be nouriſhed, &amp; hath alſo ſhaken of that great infarced, and ſtuffed waight, which the ſtomacke vſed to fill it ſelfe, and ſatiſfie appetite withall.</p>
            <p>But no man will doubt, that this moſt pure nouriſhment is vnited with the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb facs="tcp:14860:13"/>
and that it is entangled, &amp; doth grow with all the members and ioyntes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and that it, which is not ſo, but is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to nature, doth periſh by and by, if it be mingled with the ſtrongeſt partes of the body, or doth deſtroy by litle &amp; litle the ſtrength of the body, which it ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, and doth turne it into naughty, and venemous iuyſe, as a thing whiche brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth nothing agréeable and holeſome to nouriſhe the body withall.</p>
            <p>And the greateſt argumente of this thing is, becauſe that either griefe, or daungers, or death doth thervpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inuade bodies, if with an eger appetit they ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe with their meate ſome poyſon, or other thing, which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whiche without peraduenture brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth deſtruction to the whole bodye. For truelye thoſe thinges, which are nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, are nouriſhed with thoſe thinges, wherewith they bée acquainted and bée naturall, but are deſtroyed with thoſe thinges, which be repugnant to their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>If then by the diſcorde of theſe thinges, which do ſtriue with the nature of liuing creatures, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> naturall nouriſhment alſo is corrupted, and doth take neither al thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:14860:13"/>
things, which be miniſtred to the body, nor yet any thing vpon a ſodayne to the increaſe of the fleſh, but that only, which being purified by all concoctions com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth pure, and therfore ſheweth it ſelfe fit to nouriſhe the partes: it is plaine, enough that nothing which is againſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true, can be vnited to thoſe creatures, to whom that meat is not both naturall, &amp; agreable: but that either it is caſt downe rawe, and corrupt through the belly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged into ſome other ioyce, or if it doe longe continue in the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers it doeth bréede ſome fault, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe harde to be cured, corrupting either the naturall nouriſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or elſe the fleſh, which hath néede of nouriſhment.</p>
            <p>And if it be driuen awaye with medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, or ouercome with better dyet, or naturall ſtrength, yet it will not departe out of the body without ſome ſmal hurt, as bringing nothing auaylable for lacke of abilitie to growe, &amp; to be ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with it.</p>
            <p>To be ſhort if anye man graunt nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment to be ſubminiſtred therby, and adde, there withall that it is vſuall, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in déede it be contrary to nature, that it be digeſted, and changed into anye
<pb facs="tcp:14860:14"/>
thing that is moyſte, or drye, or hote, or coulde, yet although theſe thinges bée graunted, it ſhall not folowe, that any furtherance commeth thereby to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of thoſe which riſe againe, that they get therby a fuller number of members, ſéeing that it is neither a part of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, nor yeldeth the likeneſſe, or ſtéede of any parte of the bodye, nor yet doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ſtill with the members nouriſhed, or if it do riſe againe together with the members ryſing againe, it doeth profite nothing to the vſe of life, whether it be blood, fleame, choler, or ſpirite. For then the bodies, whiche were nouriſhed ſhall not now haue néede of that, which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time they néeded, when hunger, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption being paſt, the neceſſitye of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king nouriſhment ſhalbe taken awaye.</p>
            <p>Now if any man imagine, that ſuche tranſmitation of meate doeth extende it ſelfe to the creation of fleſhe, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding neceſſitye ſhall not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, that this fleſhe being newlye crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of nouriſhment, when it commeth to the body of an other, muſt retourne again to abſolue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perfection of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer body, as a parte of it: becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſhe which hath receyued this nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:14860:14"/>
from ſome other body, neither doth kéepe it long, nor that whiche commeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another, doth long abyde there why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it commeth, but to the contrary ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth a great alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when ſometime it vaniſheth away by gréefe, ſometime it pineth awaye by care, ſorowe, labour, and ſickeneſſe, and ſometime by reaſon of the vntemperatneſſe of heat and colde, the humours do not chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge themſelues into fleſh and fatneſſe, ſo that the bodyes which haue receyued theſe meats, do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ſtill the ſame that they are.</p>
            <p>Séeing that ſuch thinges happen in the affections of the fleſhe, you maye muche more eaſily perceyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame in the fleſhe whiche is nouriſhed wyth improper meats, ſéeing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſomtime increaſeth to a huge bigneſſe, and couereth it with fat by reaſon of the meates, which are taken and agayne caſteth it awaye by ſome meanes, &amp; is diminiſhed either for ſome one, or for manye of thoſe cauſes whiche wée haue before rehearſed, ſo that that fleſh only remayneth, which hath ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth to binde, to thicke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to cheriſh, namely ſuche as is choſen of nature, and is like and agréeable to thoſe meats, wherwith according to nature, nature furniſheth
<pb facs="tcp:14860:15"/>
life, and ſuſteyneth the labours of life.</p>
            <p>But neither, as the right is, whether thoſe thinges whiche we haue ſpoken of be cleanſed away, or whether they be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, can that bée prooued to be true, which is obiected by theſe men, neither can mens bodies be mingled &amp; coupled with bodyes of the ſame kinde, whether in eating they be beguyled by ſome ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s guyle, ſo that they feele not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> taſte ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, or elſe voluntaryly for hunger, or by reaſon of madneſſe do pollute the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with deuouring bodyes of their owne kinde, vnleſſe peraduenture wée knowe not that there be ſome beaſtes indued with the ſhape of men, or compounded of diuerſe natures, ſo that they conſiſt part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye of men, partly of beaſtes, ſuch as the bouldeſt of the <hi>Poets</hi> are woont to fayne.</p>
            <p>But what ſhall I ſaye of thoſe bodyes which are geuen to no liuing creature to deuoure, and which onely for the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of their nature haue obtayned the honour of buriall, ſéeing that the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of all things hath aſſigned to no crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture any bodye of like forme for meate, although according to nature they are fedde with bodies of diuerſe forme.</p>
            <p>If ſo be that, they can declare, that the
<pb facs="tcp:14860:15"/>
fleſh of men is geuen to men for meate by the ordinaunce of nature, what impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment ſhall there be, why there ſhoulde not be mutuall ſlaughters of vs commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as is accuſtomed to be done in things graunted by nature.</p>
            <p>And truely, let them, which dare ſaye thus, rauenouſly deuoure the bodyes of their deareſt friendes as moſte deyntye meate, that they may eate them, whome they loued beſt.</p>
            <p>But if this be vngodly, and an haynous, and abominable offence to be ſpoken, &amp; to bée deteſted aboue all other wicked meates and miſchieuouſe actes, for man to deuoure the limmes of men, &amp; againe if it be true, that that whiche is againſt nature, is not receiued of the hungry me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and that which is not receyued for meate, cannot growe together with thoſe bodyes, for whiche it is not meate natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally: it cannot be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mens bodies at any time ſhould be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded with other bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the ſame kinde, into who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye to nature they are thruſt for meate, although they be ſtuffed into their belies by reaſon of ſome gréeuous calamitie.</p>
            <p>For flying backe and refuſing nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue facultye, and being caſt thither, from
<pb facs="tcp:14860:16"/>
whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce they had their firſt beginning, are ioyned to their firſt grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des for a time, &amp; yet being ſeuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence by the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedome &amp; power of him, which ordreth al things, they ſhalbe ioyned one to another again in moſt conuenient order, whether they haue béene burnte with fire, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed with water, or deuoured of beaſts or being cut of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the body of him, which is yet aliue, waxed rotten before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other partes: yet comming together agayne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt themſelues they ſhall poſſeſſe the ſame place, that they maye make the ſame proportion and conſtitution of the body, and repayre the reſurrection &amp; the life of the bodye being dead or all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſſolued.</p>
            <p>It is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient to proſequute theſe thinges at large: for they haue a declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion confeſſed and not doubted of, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally among ſuch men, as do hate beaſtly and brutiſhe cuſtomes.</p>
            <p>But ſéeing their be many thinges pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to the ſearching out of theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: firſt of all I wiſh them to be exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, which runne to humane workes, &amp; to men, the makers thereof, whoſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes being worne out, or rotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by reaſon of time, or cleane vndone by ſome other
<pb facs="tcp:14860:16"/>
meane cannot be renewed again by a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude drawne their hence, do go about to prooue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God either will not, or if hée will, can not reſtore a dead and vaniſhed karcas to his former ſtate: neither do they conſider with them ſelues, that by this meanes, they be contumeliouſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, whilſt they compare powers differing one from an other in euery re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte, or rather the poſſeſſours of the powers, and do compare thinges artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall with thinges naturall.</p>
            <p>It is not without fault earneſtlye to deale with ſuch men. For it is a fooliſhe thing in déede to gaynſaye light, &amp; vayne perſons: but it is a great deale more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, &amp; of al other the trueſt to affirme that to be poſſible to God, which is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wherfore if either by theſe thinges whiche are probable, or by all thoſe things, which be heretofore exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, reaſon doth declare it to bée poſſible to God, it is manifeſt enough, that it muſt not be counted impoſſible, or to abhorre from the will of God.</p>
            <p>For what he will not do, therfore hée will not do it, either becauſe it is vniuſt, or els becauſe it is vnworthy.</p>
            <p>Furthermore this iniuſtice is percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,
<pb facs="tcp:14860:17"/>
either about him, which ryſeth, or about ſome other thing without him.</p>
            <p>But it is manifeſte, that there is no iniury done to any thing at all, which is without thoſe, that riſe againe, and are exiſtent in nature. For the intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible creatures do receiue no iniurye by the reſurrection of men, for there being is nothing therby hindered, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of men doth bring no reproch or hurt to them, as it doth ſeme not to do alſo vnto thinges without reaſon, and ſoule.</p>
            <p>For they after the reſurrection ſhall not remayne, and to ſuch thinges which be not, can no wrong be done.</p>
            <p>But if you do imagine them to be, then yet ſhall they féele no wrong by the reſurrection of men.</p>
            <p>For if when they are beſtowed on the nature of man, and be broughte vnder yooke, and all kinde of ſeruitude, for the behoofe of them, being ſubiect vnto mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerye, do yet ſuffer no wrong, much leſſe ſhall they ſuffer iniury, when man ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be made incorruptible, and be placed frée from all néede, and miſery, and they alſo deliuered from all kinde of ſeruitude.</p>
            <p>For if they were endued with the gifte
<pb facs="tcp:14860:17"/>
of ſpeaking, they woulde not accuſe the maker of all thinges, as though contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye to right they were placed vnder the condicion of men, becauſe they were not admitted into the fellowſhip of the ſame reſurrection.</p>
            <p>For to thoſe thinges, whoſe nature is not equall, he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is iuſt, doth not attribute one ende or honour, &amp; where is no ſenſe of iuſtice as in brute beaſtes, and things without life, there is no indignation for any in iuſtice.</p>
            <p>This alſo can not be ſayd, that in man any iniurye is perceyued by that hée is rayſed from the dead.</p>
            <p>For he, as he is framed of ſoule, and bodye, ſo he receyueth iniurye againſte other parte, other bodye, or ſoule, and a wiſe man will not affirme the ſoule to ſuffer iniury therefore, becauſe by this meanes it doeth not retayne the ſame trade of life, in which nowe in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent worlde it liueth.</p>
            <p>For if nowe, dwelling in a corruptible body, and ſubiect to paſſions, it ſuffereth no iniury, much leſſe dwelling in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible body, &amp; ſubiect to no paſſions, ſhall it abide any wrong.</p>
            <p>Nay, farther then this, euen the bodye
<pb facs="tcp:14860:18"/>
féeleth no iniurie. For if nowe being cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, and ioyned in fellowſhip with an incorruptible ſoule, it taketh no wrong thereby, muche leſſe ſhall it take wrong, when on both ſides they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible.</p>
            <p>Furthermore neither can this be ſaid, that it is an vnworthye thyng for God, that he ſhould reſtore and gather againe reſolued bodies.</p>
            <p>For if that, which is leſſe in dignity (na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely to create a mortall bodye, ſubiect to affections) did not ſéeme vnworthye God, much leſſe ſhall it bée vnworthy for him to bring that into the worlde, which is more excellente, and endued with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie, and fréenes from paſſions.</p>
            <p>If therfore by thoſe things, which are firſt in nature, &amp; thoſe alſo, which conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly do follow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt, euery point, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che was in queſtion, be plainly ſhewed, &amp; declared: it is manifeſt enough, that the reſtoring of bodyes is ſuch as is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of God, and which he both will and can bring to paſſe.</p>
            <p>For by theſe thinges the falſitie of the contraries, and the abſurditie of them, which beléeue not is declared.</p>
            <p>For what néede is there to ſpeake of
<pb facs="tcp:14860:18"/>
the mutuall agrée of one thing with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of the mutuall coherence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene them, as though they were ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by ſome diuerſity, and it were not lawfull to ſaye that what God will, that he can do, and is for his maieſtie, to do with dignitie.</p>
            <p>But wée haue ſayde before that there is one diſputation co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the trueth, another in defence of the trueth, &amp; haue declared wherein one of them differeth from an other, and when, and amongſt whom it profiteth.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding it will nothing hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vs, for common, ſafties ſake and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that thoſe thinges, which haue béene ſaide may agrée with thoſe thinges that ſhalbe ſaide, to take our beginning from the ſelfe ſame thinges, and ſuche as are congruente vnto them: for it behooueth the one by nature to haue the prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, &amp; the other in ſtéede of a wayting man to make waye for the chiefe. And with his waymaking which goeth before to take awaye all hinderaunces and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedimentes.</p>
            <p>For the treatiſe which is of the trueth, ſéeing it is neceſſary for all men, both for their ſafegarde, and preſeruation is firſt
<pb facs="tcp:14860:19"/>
and chiefe, both by nature, order, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite: by nature becauſe it ſetteth foorth the knowledge of thinges: by order, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is in, and together with thoſe thinges, the iudgement and knowledge wherof it promiſeth: by profite, becauſe it maketh defence and ſafegarde to them which knowe and learne it.</p>
            <p>But the diſcourſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whiche is for the trueth, is inferiour both in nature and power: for it is leſſe to reproue a falſhood then to eſtabliſhe a trueth, and followeth by order.</p>
            <p>For it exerciſeth force againſt them, which beléeue the falſhoode. But a falſe opinion groweth, and procéedeth of a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſowing, as it were, &amp; of corruption.</p>
            <p>But although theſe thinges be thus, yet ſomtime this is put before the other, and is more profitable, becauſe it taketh away, and forepurgeth troubleſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulitye, or ſome new doubt, or ſome falſe opinion, and both theſe tende to one ende.</p>
            <p>For both ſéeketh godlines, as well that which refuſeth the falſeſhood, as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which eſtabliſheth the truth, &amp; yet are they not all one. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one is neceſſary, as I ſaid, for all beléeuers, and them whiche haue
<pb facs="tcp:14860:19"/>
anye care of the trueth, &amp; their owne ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, the other is more profitable in ſome time and among ſome men.</p>
            <p>Theſe thinges are ſpoken briefely, to kéepe the remembraunce of the former woordes.</p>
            <p>But nowe we muſt retourne to oure purpoſe, and declare that that treatiſe is true, which is concerning the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and that vpon that cauſe, for the whiche, and by the which the firſt man &amp; his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours were borne, although they were not both created after one maner.</p>
            <p>Then we muſt prooue it by the nature of all men, in that they be men.</p>
            <p>Afterwarde by the iudgement of the creatour, which he will geue of them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as they haue liued, whiche iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement no man will doubt of, but that it is moſt iuſt.</p>
            <p>But the handling of the cauſe doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſte in this point, that wée ſearche out, whether man were made vnaduiſedlye, and to no ende, or for ſome purpoſe.</p>
            <p>If he were created for ſome purpoſe, whether it were that he ſhould liue, and continue in this life, the, whiche hée was naturally ordeyned vnto, or that hée ſhould miniſter ſome profit to an other.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14860:20"/>
But if he were created for ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, whether it were for the profite of the creator, or of ſome other thing whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che belongeth to the creatour, &amp; is more regarded of him, then man.</p>
            <p>Here truely, vſing a common and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple kinde of ſearching in beholding of thinges wée finde, that whoſoeuer is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with reaſon, and is mooued to do any thing by reaſonable iudgement, doth nothing vnaduiſedlye, of thoſe thinges, which he doth willingly.</p>
            <p>For that he doth, he taketh in hande, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for his owne ſake, or for ſome ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſake, whiche he loueth, or inflamed with the deſire and naturall inclination to that thing, which he hath done.</p>
            <p>As for example (For we will vſe a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude that our purpoſe may be playn) A man buyldeth a houſe, and that for his owne proper vſe; hee furniſheth alſo his houſe being in order; with Camels and other beaſtes, whoſe helpe he hath néede of, not for his owne vſe as it ſéemeth (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the latter end be referred to him) but as touching the next &amp; néereth cauſe, for their commoditie whome hée careth for.</p>
            <p>But he begetteth children, not for his
<pb facs="tcp:14860:20"/>
owne vſe, nor for the profit of any thing, which belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth vnto him, but that thoſe, whom he begetteth, may be &amp; remayne aliue, as farre as it is lawfull, and maye be done, miniſtring a remedye to his owne death by the ſucceſſion of children, &amp; beléeuing thus farre, that he hath put of mortalitie.</p>
            <p>But God neither created man vnad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſedly, ſéeing he is wiſe. (For a wiſe man doth no thing vnaduiſedlye) neither for his owne vſe &amp; neceſſity (for he hath nede of nothing) &amp; that which hath néed of nothing, doth not deſire profite of thoſe thinges which he createth) neither dyd he make man for the profite of any other of his woorkes, for nothing amongſt thoſe thinges, which are endued with reaſon and iudgement, whether it be great or ſmall, is created or ſhalbe created for the vſe of any other thing. For ſuche thinges are created only for theyr owne life and ſafetye.</p>
            <p>Neither hath reaſon found out any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end, why men were created, ſéeing that they were ordeyned to be immortall without y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> néede of any thing, ſéeing that they require no helpe of men for the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of their life, &amp; ſéeing that all beaſts
<pb facs="tcp:14860:21"/>
be ſubiecte, and all thinges elſe do mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter commoditie to men, for whoſe vſe they were made.</p>
            <p>But beaſtes haue no vſe of men: for neither is it, nor was it at any time law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to debaſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> creature, which is chiefe &amp; ruler of all, for the vſe of other thinges whiche are vnder him, or to bring that which is endued with reaſon, vnder the yoke of thoſe thinges, which be without reaſon and vnfit to rule.</p>
            <p>Wherfore, if man were created neither without cauſe, nor vnaduiſedly, nor to no end, (for there is nothing amongſt the woorkes of God done vnaduiſedly, if we conſider the meaning and intention of God) nor yet for the profite of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> creator, nor for the commoditie of other thinges, whiche the creatour made, it is manifeſt enough that if we looke vpon the firſt and vniuerſall cauſe, GOD created man for himſelfe, and his owne goodneſſe &amp; wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, whiche you may eaſily perceyue in all thinges created: but if you ſearche out the next cauſe, and that which agréeth with men being created, you ſhall finde that man was borne to this ende, that he ſhoulde liue.</p>
            <p>But not in ſuch a life that ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb facs="tcp:14860:21"/>
for a while, &amp; ſtraight way ſhoulde periſh for euer.</p>
            <p>For God (I thinke) hath geuen ſuch a life to beaſtes that créepe, and to birdes, and to fiſhes: but to them which beare about them his owne Image, and there withal haue a minde which is the finder out of things, and are adorned with the giftes of reaſon, he hath aſſigned a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall continuaunce, that by knowing their creator, and following his power and wiſedome by lawes and iuſtice, they might with thoſe vertues happyly continue euerlaſtingly, with which they eſtabliſhed their former life, when they yet liued in their earthly, and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bodies.</p>
            <p>For ſuch thinges as are created for the behoofe of other thinges, when thoſe thinges, for whoſe vſe they were ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned do periſh, do not without cauſe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe alſo, and can not remayne for any purpoſe, becauſe ther is no place amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt thinges created of God, for vaine idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>But thoſe thinges which were for this end created, that they ſhould be and continue (the cauſe being ioyned and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled with their nature, ſéeing the
<pb facs="tcp:14860:22"/>
cauſe doth onely exacte and require, that they ſhould bée) it is not poſſible that they ſhould at any time ſuffer ſuch vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, wherby they ſhould vtterly bée a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, ſéeing that this cauſe is vnderſtoode by a perpetuall kinde of being, and doth conſiſt in this poynt, it is neceſſary that that creature do remaine in ſafetie, which was thus created, and do and ſuffer thoſe thinges which bée a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréeable to the nature thereof, both the partes whereof it conſiſteth, doing that which in them lyeth, ſo that the minde doth continue and remaine inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riable in the nature wherin it was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. For it was therfore created, to bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell the affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the body, &amp; to eſtéeme with ſéemely iudgement, and meaſure, with vpright meaſures whatſoeuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falleth: But the body was ordeyned to this ende, that it ſhould incline it ſelfe to ſuche thinges, as be naturall, &amp; receyue thoſe alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which are attributed to it by nature, and that amongeſt other chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges, which happen vnto it, either in age, or beautie, or bigneſſe, it ſhould ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the reſurrection.</p>
            <p>For the reſurrection is a kinde of
<pb facs="tcp:14860:22"/>
chaunge, and that the laſt of all, and alſo the alteration into a better thing, which then ſhalbe in the bodies of them, which be a liue.</p>
            <p>We are as ſure of theſe things, as we are of them, which haue already happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and conſidering our owne nature, wee do not beare impacientlye this our néedy, and corruptible life, as agréeable to this preſent world, and we conſtantly hoope for Eternitie of life, rydde of all corruption, whiche wée do not grounde vpon the inuentions of men, féeding our ſelues with a vayne hope, but we beleue an vnfayned and ſufficient witneſſe (na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melye the reaſon and ordinaunce of the creatour) according to the which, he hath framed man of a ſoule immortall, and a body, which alſo he hath endued with reaſon and equitye, geuen by nature to conſerue, and kéepe his giftes, and thoſe things, which be agréeable to a diſcrete life, and a minde endued with reaſon.</p>
            <p>Whereby we knowe well enough, that God would not haue ordeyned ſuch a creature, nor furniſhed it with all thinges neceſſarye for perpetuall conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, if he would not haue it continue, which he had in ſuch ſorte created.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14860:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Wherefore, if the maker of the world created ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he ſhould vſe wiſedome in all his doinges, and that being made a beholder of his magnificence, and wiſedome, whiche he declared in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye place: with the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>templation of theſe thinges ſhould continue, and that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his purpoſe, and will, and the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which he ingendered in them, truly the cauſe of the creation doth confirme, and make credible an endleſſe continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce, and this continuance a reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without the which man cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue.</p>
            <p>It is manifeſt therfore by thoſe things which haue béen ſpoken, namely by the cauſe of the beginning, and the will of the creatour, that the reſurrection is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed.</p>
            <p>Séeing that therfore the cauſe is ſuch, why man was brought into the world, it ſhalbe now expedient to conſider thoſe thinges which by naturall order, do fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the former reaſons.</p>
            <p>For if we weigh, and conſider this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, the nature of men created doth followe the cauſe of their creation, and the iuſte iudgemente of the creatour vpon them, doth followe the nature of
<pb facs="tcp:14860:23"/>
men created, and after all theſe, follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the end, why they liue.</p>
            <p>Séeing that therefore thoſe thinges, which go before be playnly declared, the nature of men muſt be hereafter decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and that either by true opinions, or by inquiſitions, what ſorte ſoeuer they be of.</p>
            <p>That demonſtration doth get a credite not inconſtant to thoſe thinges whiche are ſpoken, whiche hath his beginning not from ſome thing, or place, which is without the matter, or doth ariſe of the opinions, or decrees of others: but doth ariſe of common vnderſtanding, or is gathered by the conſequence of thoſe thinges, which be laſt, to them which be firſt.</p>
            <p>For that, is either of the firſt decrées, or of thoſe thinges, which only by war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, do ſtirre vp, and as it were, rayſe out of ſléepe naturall vnderſtanding, or of thoſe thinges, which naturally in fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip do cleaue vnto the firſt decrées, and be of naturall conſequence.</p>
            <p>And it behooueth him, which declareth this order, to make playne, what doth follow conſequently the firſt, or the laſt, in déede that he do not neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly handle
<pb facs="tcp:14860:24"/>
either the trueth, or ſome aſſertion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeding from the trueth, neither confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thoſe thinges whiche be repugnant in nature, or peruert the naturall order of thinges.</p>
            <p>Wherfore, I thinke it expediente for them which take paine in this argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and do deſire wiſely to determine, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ther be any reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of mens bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, firſt to conſider the force of thoſe thinges, whiche do make this demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, the partes being compared to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and what place euery thing doth obtaine, and what difference is betwéen theſe thinges, and the firſt, ſeconde, and thirde, and laſt of all what doeth conſiſte in the laſt place. In placing of theſe thinges in order, it behooueth that the cauſe be declared why man was created that is to ſay, the minde and purpoſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> creator, for the which he tooke in hande to create man. Afterwarde, the nature of man (which in order obteyneth the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde place) muſte bée fitlye placed and applyed, partly becauſe we cannot iudge of both at once, partlye becauſe they bée both together, &amp; do bring the ſame fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to this preſent purpoſe: partly alſo becauſe by theſe thinges, as chiefe, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:14860:24"/>
principall, and drawing their beginning from the workemanſhip of God, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection is playnly declared: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding by the rule of wiſedome alſo a man maye gather the certentye of this thing.</p>
            <p>I ſay the rule of wiſedome doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſte in this, that rewardes, and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes according to iuſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, may be beſtowed vpon euery man, according to his deſertes, and that the end of them do aunſwere to theyr life.</p>
            <p>For many which haue taken in hande to diſpute of the reſurrection, did aſſay to bring all their buſineſſe to effecte, onely for that which is thirde, thinking y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe of the reſurrection of men to be only for iudgement.</p>
            <p>But that is manifeſtly prooued falſe, becauſe that all men riſe againe, yet all that riſe againe are not iudged.</p>
            <p>For if only the iuſtice of iudgemente be the cauſe of the reſurrection, it ſhould neceſſarylye followe, that they, whiche haue not at all offended, or haue commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted notable actes in their liues, ſhould be exempt from the reſurrection, and they alſo, which in the beginning of their age, do ende their life, which they themſelues
<pb facs="tcp:14860:25"/>
alſo thinke ſufficient, that the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be not for iudgement, according to the principall cauſe, but according to the determination, and appointment of the creatour, and the nature of that, which is created.</p>
            <p>But ſéeing that the onely cauſe of the creation of man doth ſuffice, if it be well looked vpon, to confirme the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which by the naturall guyding of reaſon doth followe the bodies being diſſolued, yet peraduenture it ſhalbe reaſon to omit nothing of thoſe, which we haue ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and to declare in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the power &amp; efficaſie of the cauſes, then afterwarde of thoſe thinges that followe, for the behoofe of ſuch men, as cannot perceyue thoſe thinges by their owne wit, and amongſt other things to ſet foorth the nature of men created, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che doth leade vs to the knowledge of the ſame matter, and doth bréede as great credite to the reſurrection.</p>
            <p>For if the whole nature of man doth conſiſt of an immortal ſoule, and a body made fit according to his creation, and if God haue attributed neither to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule by it ſelfe, nor to the bodye alone, ſuche a beginning or life, but vnto perfit men,
<pb facs="tcp:14860:25"/>
which are made of both theſe parts, that whileſt they liue, vſing the ſame partes, of the which they receyued their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and life, they mighte come to the ſame common ende, and rewarde, it is neceſſarye, ſéeing one creature is made of both theſe partes, whiche is endued with all the affections both of the minde and bodye, which doth, and exerciſeth all thinges, that requyre the iudgement ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the ſenſes or of reaſon, that the whole courſe of theſe things be referred to ſome ende, that all thinges, and in all pointes, both the beginning of man, and the nature of man, and the life of man, and whatſoeuer hée doth, or ſuffereth, &amp; the ende agréeing to his nature, do run together to one conſente, and mutuall combination.</p>
            <p>But if there be one conſent, or harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of euery liuing creature, and a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual paſſion, and participation of affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, both of thoſe which haue theyr be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning from the minde, as alſo of thoſe which procéede from the body, it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that in all theſe, there remaine one ende, and one rewarde, but there ſhalbe one ende in déede, when the ſame crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhall conſiſt of both his partes, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
<pb facs="tcp:14860:26"/>
ſhall happen for the endes ſake: but the ſame creature ſhall perfitly conſiſt, when thoſe thinges ſhalbe preſent with it, and thoſe partes reſtored to it, by the which his perfitneſſe is abſolued.</p>
            <p>But the renuing of the ſame men, doth declare that the reſurrection of dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies doth neceſſaryly followe, whether the ſelfe ſame partes can not bee natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ioyned together, or the ſame men reſtored, or returne again to their owne nature.</p>
            <p>If therefore, minde and reaſon be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to men, to the ende that they ſhoulde iudge, not onely of intelligible, ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces but of the wiſedome, iuſtice, &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of him, that gaue theſe thinges: it is neceſſary that if thoſe things remayne for whoſe ſake this reaſonable iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was geuen, reaſonable iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhould alſo remayne, whiche was geuen to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerne thoſe thinges.</p>
            <p>But it is impoſſible y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this iudgement ſhould co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue, vnleſſe that the nature do eke continue, which kepeth &amp; cheriſheth it, in the ſeate &amp; reſting place therof: but man is he, which receyueth wit &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon into him, and not the ſoule by it ſelfe, therfore it muſt néedes be, that man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting
<pb facs="tcp:14860:26"/>
of both partes, do continue for euer. But it is impoſſible for him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue for euer, vnleſſe he riſe agayne. For vnleſſe a reſurrection be a meane, man in no caſe can endure. And if the nature of man can not endure, the ſoule was in vayne mingled with the néedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the body &amp; the accidents, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections therof.</p>
            <p>The bodye alſo is in vayne vnto the ſoule, geuing place to the regiment ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and is bridled by it to the ende it may obtaine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing, which it deſireth. And in vaine is minde, in vayne wiſedome, in vaine the obſeruation of iuſtice, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of vertue among men, and the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing, and diſpoſing of lawes, is to no purpoſe. And to be ſhort, what ſoeuer is commendable in men, &amp; by mens pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement, is in vayne. Yea, &amp; that which is greater, the very engendring and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of men is in vayne.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, if all vaineneſſe bee all together excluded from all the workes of God, and his function, it is neceſſary that the continuance of the bodye in hys nature be coeternall with the immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the ſoule.</p>
            <p>Let no man maruayle, that wée call
<pb facs="tcp:14860:27"/>
life cutten in ſunder by death, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, a continewing, ſith wee are not ignoraunt, that there is not one only ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of the worde, nor one only ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of continewing, and no maruayle ſéeing the nature of thinges continuing, is not all one. For euery thing according to the nature therof hath her proper con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance. You ſhall not finde in thoſe things which are wholly incorruptible, and immortall, a like, and vniforme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuaunce, becauſe the ſubſtaunces of the things aboue, are not like the things beneath.</p>
            <p>Neither is it conuenient to require in men a continuaunce euer like vnto it ſelf, indiſtinct without any variety, as in thoſe thinges is, which from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning were created immortall, and do onely by the appoyntment of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor continue euerlaſtingly, but that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue their continnaunce according to the ſoule from their creation without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny alteration or chaunge. But according to the nature of the body, men haue im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie by a chaunge. For the cauſe of the reſurrection doth require it, &amp; loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thervpon, wée looke for the diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the body, as it, which followeth
<pb facs="tcp:14860:27"/>
this néedy, and corruptible life, and after ward we hope for an incorruptible con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance without alteration, neither making our end like to the end of bruite beaſtes, neither to the continuaunce of thoſe thinges, which be immortall, leſt for the lacke of knowledge in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we make the nature and life of men equall, and like to thoſe thinges, which we ought not.</p>
            <p>Wée muſt not therfore be troubled. If there be any inequality eſpied in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duration of men, neither oughte wée to diſpayre of the reſurrection, when the ſeparating of the ſoule from her bodylye members, and the diſſoluing of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyly members from it do diſpart the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall tenoure of the life.</p>
            <p>For although the bringing a ſléepe of the ſenſes, &amp; of other naturall ſtrengths, which naturally doth ariſe in mans reſt, &amp; for a ſeaſon do ſlumber, and in a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner are again reuiued, do ſéeme to cut a ſunder the ſenſible life, yet wée do not refuſe to count it a life, for which cauſe, I thinke, ſome men dooe call ſléepe the brother of death, not becauſe they would therby declare the ſtocke of them as though they came of one aunceters, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:14860:28"/>
parentes, but becauſe like thinges hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to them, which be a ſléepe, and to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which be dead in reſpecte of the reſt and quietneſſe of the ſenſes, when they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande nothing of thinges preſent, or which are then done, nay they perceyue not themſelues either to be, or to liue.</p>
            <p>If therfore wee do not refuſe, to call the life of man, being full of ſuche ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualitie euen from mans birth vnto his death, &amp; interrupted by all thoſe meanes which we haue before rehearſed, a life: then ought we not to diſpayre of the life, which is ordeyned to ſuccéede our diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which bringeth together with it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, although for a ſeaſon it be cutte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſunder, by the departure of the ſoule from the body.</p>
            <p>For the nature of men poſſeding from the beginning, and that according to the decrée of the creatour, an inequalitie attributed vnto it, hath an vnequall lyfe, and a continuance, diſtinct ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time by ſléepe, ſometime by death, &amp; by diuerſe alterations of ages, ſo that the firſt do not playnlye appeare, when the laſt do ſodenlye come vpon them.</p>
            <p>For who woulde beléeue, vnleſſe he were taught by experience of thinges,
<pb facs="tcp:14860:28"/>
that ſo great force lyeth hid in the moiſt and ſofte ſéede, or that ſuch diuerſitye of bigneſſe, and greatneſſe, whiche ariſeth and is framed therof, is hidde therin, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely of bones, ſinewes, griſtles, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of muſcles, fleſhe, and bowelles, and other partes of the bodie?</p>
            <p>For in the ſéede, being yet moiſt, a man can perceyue no ſuche thing, nor in chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be thoſe thinges perceyued, which in young men do encreaſe, nor thoſe thinges do appeare in youth, whiche the eſtate of man poſſeſſeth: nor agayne in the ſtate of man, which age hath.</p>
            <p>But although amongſt thoſe thinges, which are ſayde before, ſome do nothing at all, and ſome but obſcurelye declare the naturall chaunges, and alterations comming on men, yet notwithſtanding they, which are not blinded with naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe, and ſluggiſhneſſe, do know, what we muſt iudge of theſe things. For firſt of all it is requyred, that the ſéede bée ſowen, afterwarde when, it is ſeparated into partes, &amp; ioyntes, &amp; the young ones being nowe faſhioned do come to light, receyue in their firſt age height, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their height the abſolute perfection of the whole bodye, after a while commeth
<pb facs="tcp:14860:29"/>
on the naturall decreaſing of ſtrength, which prolongeth it ſelfe euen vnto old age, then at the laſt, when the bodies are worne awaye, diſſolution commeth on.</p>
            <p>Like as therefore in this buſineſſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſéede by any likeneſſe, or ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, doth declare, either the life, or forme of man, nor the life doth foreſhewe the diſſolution, wherwith the ioyning toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of partes ſhalbe reſolued into the firſt element, yet the order, and guyding of naturall euentes doth get credit to thoſe thinges, which in their owne ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parence, and ſhew, do ſéeme to deſerue no credite: euen ſo reaſon by ſearching the naturall conſequence, finding the trueth, doth eſtabliſhe the reſurrection, (which is much more certayne, then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, to prooue thoſe ſayinges, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with a litle before we endeuoured to get credite to the reſurrection) and that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore becauſe we are all of one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> kindred, as procéeding fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one &amp; the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> beginning. For our beginning procée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from the procreation of our firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, whome God created.</p>
            <p>But ſome men eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the beginning, whence they come are eſtabliſhed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue, other ſome following nature, and
<pb facs="tcp:14860:29"/>
the life of man, as their guide, do get be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leife, of the wiſedome of God toward vs.</p>
            <p>For the cauſe, according to the which, and for the which me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were borne, agrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the nature of men, doth obteine her force, by the workemanſhip of man created.</p>
            <p>But the cauſe of iuſtice, according to the which God will iudge men, whether they liue well, or ill, doth take his force from the ende of men. For therefore are men borne. But it dependeth rather vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the prouidence of God.</p>
            <p>Séeing that therefore thoſe thinges be declared, and prooued by vs, as fare as we coulde, which were of the firſt order, let vs declare nowe alſo thoſe thinges that follow. But I ſpeake of the reward and puniſhment, which according to iuſt iudgement, ſhalbe beſtowed vppon eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man according to his deſertes, and of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſhalbe correſpondent to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of man. But let that bée done in ſuch order, that ſuch thinges go before, as be naturally of the firſt place, and firſt let vs entreate of the cauſe of the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which words we therefore ſpeake, becauſe we haue a care of the cheife ſtay and order of this diſputation in hande,
<pb facs="tcp:14860:30"/>
and becauſe it behooueth them, which admit God, as the creatour of the whole worlde, to attribute the charge, &amp; care of all thinges to his wiſedome, and iuſtice, if ſo be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they will ſticke vnto the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation appointed, &amp; the principles once allowed.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, ſéeing they be of this opinion, it is reaſon, that they thinke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing either of thinges terreſtriall, or celeſtiall to be deſtitute of the care and prouidence of God, but that the care of the creatour doth extende it ſelfe vnto all thinges indifferentlye, as well vnto thoſe which be open, as thoſe, which be hid, and vnto thoſe, which be great, as thoſe which be ſmal. For al things, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che be, haue neede of the prouidence of their creatour, but euerye thing pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly according to his nature, &amp; for that purpoſe, for which it was created.</p>
            <p>For I do not thinke it expedient, with much labour particularly to declare, and diſtinguiſh with diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, what is agrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the nature of euery thing. Man truely, of whom we nowe entreate, as he is hungry, hath néede of meate, as hée is mortall, hath néede of ſucceſſion of children, as he is endued with reaſon,
<pb facs="tcp:14860:30"/>
hath néede of iudgement.</p>
            <p>But he hath néede of iudgement, that he may lawfully labour for liuing, and ſucceſſion.</p>
            <p>But it is neceſſary, that ſéeing ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, and ſucceſſion do pe rtayne to that, which conſiſteth of both partes, iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t alſo do perteyn to the ſame. But I call that whiche is compounde of both partes, a man conſiſting of a ſoule, and a body, and ſuch a man to be accuſed of all thinges, which he doth, ſo that he recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth either a rewarde, or puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for them.</p>
            <p>If therefore the ſentence of iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be pronounced againſt that, which conſiſteth of both parts, according to his doinges, it cannot be, that the ſoule alone ſhould receyue either rewarde, or puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhement for thoſe thinges, which it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted with the body.</p>
            <p>For the ſoule by it ſelfe is not touched with thoſe offences, which are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the pleaſures of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body, or meate, or apparell: neither muſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body receyue rewarde, or puniſhment, becauſe it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyueth not the daunger of lawes, &amp; iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement, but man which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth of both theſe partes, muſt receyue iudgement
<pb facs="tcp:14860:31"/>
for all his doinges.</p>
            <p>But you can perceyue by no meane, that this doth happen in this life, for that is not lawfully obſerued in this preſent life, ſéeing that we ſée many, which are wicked, and abounde in all iniquitie, to perſiſt voyd of any miſfortune euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till death, &amp; we ſée them, which are well knowen for there vertue, to ſpende their life in ſuffering gréefes, vexations, ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, reproches, and al kind of affliction. Neither can you perceyue it after death, for that which conſiſteth of both partes doth not remayne, ſéeing the ſoule is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from the body, and the bodye it ſelfe diſſolued into thoſe thinges, of whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che it was firſt made, and nothing now remayneth, whiche reſerueth the olde forme, or nature, or yet the memorye of thoſe thinges, which are done.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, that which followeth is euident, namelye that (as the Apoſtle ſayth) this corruptible being diſſolued, muſt put on incorruption, that thoſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies which be dead, being made aliue by the reſurrection, and thoſe thinges being ioyned together agayne, which were caſt a ſunder, or altogether conſumed, euery man may iuſtlye receyue thoſe thinges,
<pb facs="tcp:14860:31"/>
whiche he hath committed by reaſon of the body, whether they be good, or ill.</p>
            <p>Againſt them therefore, which do ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the prouidence of God, and receyue the ſame principles, and groundes, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we do, and afterwarde (I know not howe) do ſhrinke, and reuolt from thoſe opinions, which they receyued, &amp; thought well of, you may vſe ſuch woordes, and other much more plentifull: if you will dilate at large thoſe thinges, which haue béen ſpoken briefely, &amp; in fewe wordes. But againſt ſuch, as make a doubt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the principles them ſelues, it ſhalbe good to appoint another principle, and ground before theſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the meane time wee maye imagine thinges, that maye be doubted of, and muſt be ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out by queſtions, which they doubte of, namely whether the life, and maners of men be neglected, and darkened with the groſſe ſhadowe of the earth, which hideth, and wrappeth in ignoraunce, and ſilence both the men themſelues, and alſo their déedes.</p>
            <p>Or which is much more certen, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wée muſt thinke, the creatour to be ruler of the thinges created, and to bée the obſeruer, and iudge of all thinges,
<pb facs="tcp:14860:32"/>
whiche are done, or committed, as well déedes, as thoughtes.</p>
            <p>For if there ſhall at no time be iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the actes of men, then men ſhal haue no preheminence aboue bruite beaſtes, and they ſhalbe in worſe caſe, then bruite beaſts, which do bring their affections vnder bondage, and do greatly regarde, and honour godlineſſe, iuſtice, &amp; other vertues. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarywiſe, the beaſtly and ſauage life ſhalbe counted beſt, and vertue on the other ſide a fooliſh thing, the threatens of iudgment worthy to be laughed at, and to followe pleaſure the happyeſt thing of all, &amp; that ſhalbe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the common decrée, and chiefe lawe of all men, which is pleaſant to naughty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>packes, and riotous perſons, let vs eate and drinke, for to morow wee ſhall dye.</p>
            <p>For the ende of ſuche a life, is not pleaſure, as ſome men thinke, but a full voydneſſe of perceyuing.</p>
            <p>If therfore the creatour hath ſome care of his creatures, and the iudgement of good, or euill actes ſhall at any time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch, it ſhalbe either while they do wel, or ill in this preſent life, or after death, as long as they conſiſt in diſſolution, and ſeparation. But neither waye can you
<pb facs="tcp:14860:32"/>
finde that iuſt iudgement is obſerued.</p>
            <p>For good men in this preſente life do not receyue the rewardes of vertue, nor euill men puniſhment for their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that I maye in the meane time let paſſe, that as long as the nature, wherein wée nowe are doth continue in ſafetye, the nature of man cannot abyde ſufficient puniſhment for his manifold, &amp; gréeuous offences. For when a théefe, or prince, or tyrant doth heap innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable murders of men one vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another, it cannot be, that he can make ſatiſfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for his ſinnes by one death. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo a man doth thinke nothing truely of God, and hath liued in al voluptuouſneſſe, and blaſphemie, hath deſpiſed all the diuine commaundementes, hath broken the lawes, hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted whoredome both with women, and children, hath iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly ouerthrowne Cities, hath burnt houſes with the inhabitants, hath ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led prouinces, hath deſtroyed by ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter great people, and countryes, &amp; whole nations: how can he in this corruptible body ſuffer condigne puniſhment for his deſertes, ſéeing death doth preuent his deſerued tormentes, and this mortall nature is not ſufficient to puniſh duely
<pb facs="tcp:14860:33"/>
one offence.</p>
            <p>Therfore in this preſent life, the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according to his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe, and deſert, can not be declared, nor after death, for death is a deſtroying of the whole life altogether, if the ſoule periſh, and be putrified together with the body.</p>
            <p>Or els truely the ſoule remayneth, &amp; cannot be diſſolued, nor broke in ſunder, nor corrupted, but the body is diſſolued, kéeping no longer the remembraunce of things done, or the ſenſe of ſuch things, as happen vnto it.</p>
            <p>For if the whole life of man be vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye deſtroyed, there appeareth no reſpect or care of men, neither doth there ſéeme any iudgment ordeyned for well or euill doing: but whatſoeuer wickedneſſe is in a lawleſſe life, will approch, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowe again, and other inconueniences, which ſuch a life doth bring with it, as a flocke of companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and amongſt them impietie the denyer of God, whiche is chiefe, &amp; ruler of that life, in whiche men liue without lawe.</p>
            <p>And if the body be corrupt, and as eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part is diſſolued, ſo it departeth to the elementes, which be of the ſame nature,
<pb facs="tcp:14860:33"/>
but the ſoule doth continue by it ſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupt, yet there ſhall not be place to iudge the ſoule, when iuſtice ſhall not be preſent.</p>
            <p>But it is an heynous offence to ſuſpect any iudgement to procéede from God, or of God, in which iuſtice is not preſent: but iuſtice is not preſent whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not in ſafety, and capable of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which committed iuſt, or vniuſte actes, but he that committed all thinges in his life, which muſte be iudged, was man, and not the ſoule alone, to be ſhort this kinde of dealing doth defende iuſtice in no poynt.</p>
            <p>For in receyuing rewardes for things well done, vndoubtedly the bodye ſhall ſuffer wrong, becauſe it was partaker of the trauayle in doing thinges wel, and nowe is not partaker of the honor which is rendred for well doing: and ſéeing par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don is often graunted to the ſoule for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe offences, in reſpect of the néede and neceſſitie of the body, if the body be diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted of the rewardes, for the which whileſt life laſted, it ſuffered laboures, howe ſhall it be counted not vniuſt?</p>
            <p>Contrarywiſe, if wickedneſſe be conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the ſoule ſhalbe iniuriouſlye dealte
<pb facs="tcp:14860:34"/>
withall, if it alone ſuffer puniſhemente for thoſe thinges, which it committed in life time, at the ſuggeſtion of the bodye, drawing it to his owne appetites, and motions, whileſt ſome time it is lead from that, which is honeſt by violence, ſometime by ſtealth, ſometime it is drawen by a violent inclination, &amp; ſome time it geueth it ſelfe to vices, for to gratifie, and ſlatter the fellowſhip of the bodye.</p>
            <p>Or howe, I pray you, is it not vniuſt, that the ſoule only ſhould be conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned for thoſe things, to the which according to his own nature, it hath neither deſire, nor motion, nor inclination, as ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluitie in carnall pleaſure, violence, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe, iniuſtice, &amp; other offences, which are committed for this cauſe?</p>
            <p>For if many offences be committed, becauſe men cannot well rule their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate affections, and the affections kéepe a whurly burly to this ende, that they maye helpe, and remidy the néede, and neceſſitie of the body.</p>
            <p>For they prepare all thinges for the behoofe of theſe thinges, that thereby a man may come to the vſe, and fruition, and alſo mariages are begon, and other
<pb facs="tcp:14860:34"/>
buſineſſe, which happen in the life time, in which, and about which euery thing, that is worthye either of prayſe, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſe, is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered. Where is here equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſéeing the ſoule is condemned for thoſe things, which the body is deſtrous of, and draweth the minde to the felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the ſame affection, that it maye obtayne the thing deſired? And ſéeing deſire, pleaſure, feare, gréefe, the vnru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of which affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s is ſubiect to iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement, haue their beginning from the body, notwithſtanding the offences pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeding from thence, and the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts for them, do lye vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules ſhoulders, which required no ſuch thing, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired no ſuch thing, nor feared, nor ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered any ſuch thing by it ſelfe, as man is accuſtomed to ſuffer.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, if wée ſay, that they be affections not onely of the bodye, but of man, becauſe he hath a life conſiſting of both partes: yet can we not affirme, that they pertayne to the ſoule, if wée playn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye beho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de the proper matter therof.</p>
            <p>For if it haue no néede at all of anye nouriſhment, it will neuer deſire thoſe thinges, whoſe vſe it requireth not to conſerue his being, neither will it be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhed
<pb facs="tcp:14860:35"/>
with thoſe thinges, which by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it doth not inioye, nor yet be ſorye for the want of mony, and poſſeſſions, as thinges nothing perteyning vnto it.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, if it remayne frée from corruption, it feareth nothing, that may deſtroy it. For it feareth not hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger or ſic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenes, or mayming, or mangling, or fire or ſworde, becauſe it can take no miſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, or hurt by theſe thinges, ſéeing no bodye, or that which hath a bodye, can touch it in any point.</p>
            <p>If therfore it be abſurde, to aſcribe the affections peculiarly to the ſoule, it is alſo great iniurye, and farre from the iudgement of God, to attribute the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of them to the ſoule.</p>
            <p>Beſide theſe things, which haue bene ſpoken, how, I pray you, is it not vniuſt, that although the vertues, and vices can not bée conſidered to remayne, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the ſoule, ſéeing we throughlye perceyue, that all vertues of men, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo vices contrarye to vertues, bee not in the ſoule ſeparated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bodye, and conſiſting by it ſelfe, yet we wil referre the puniſhment, and rewarde of them to the ſoules alone?</p>
            <p>Or how I praye you can a man per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue
<pb facs="tcp:14860:35"/>
valiaunce, and manlineſſe in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenturing daungers to bée onely in the mynde, whiche feareth neither death, nor wounds, nor mayming, nor hurt, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prochfull handeling, nor thoſe gréefes or miſcries which happen thereby?</p>
            <p>Or how againe can you perceiue tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraunce, and wiſedome, where no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire doth allure the minde to meat, or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall copulation, or any other pleaſure, or delight, and where nothing either diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbeth within, or prouoketh without?</p>
            <p>Or laſt of all, howe can you imagine prudence, when the matter of thinges to bée choſen, or to bée eſchued, doeth not perteyne vnto the Soules, ſéeing the matter of choyſe in doing thinges is not ſubiecte to the ſoule, or rather no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or naturall inclination is in it to do any thing.</p>
            <p>But where is there at all any fit iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice amongſte the ſoules, whether you conſider thinges of the ſame nature, or thinges externall, or from whence, or to whome, or by what means, ſhall they geue that, which is right, according to the worthyneſſe of euery man, or accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to proportion? Trulye there is no ſuch thing, if you except the honour to be
<pb facs="tcp:14860:36"/>
beſtowed by them vpon GOD, ſéeing they haue no inclination, or motion, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to vſe their owne, or abſteyne from other mens, ſéeing vſe and abſtinence is ſéene in thoſe thinges, whiche by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture haue néede of ſuch things. Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rywiſe the ſoule is ſo borne that it née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth no ſuch thing, and thence is it, that you can not perceyue the propre vſe of the members in a thing ſo ingendered.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, this is moſte abſurbe, that the lawes made, ſhould be referred to men, and the puniſhmente of the lawes wreſted to the ſoules alone.</p>
            <p>For if he whiche receyued the lawe, ought alſo rightlye receyne puniſhment for breaking the lawe, and man recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the lawe, and not the ſoule alone, it is right, that man ſuffer puniſhment for his offences, and not the ſoule alone.</p>
            <p>For truely God commaunded not the ſoules, to abſtreyne from thinges vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, as adulteries, murders, théefts, robberies, and from contempte of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, and all hurtfull, and vniuſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of other mens goodes.</p>
            <p>For this commaundement, honour thy, father and mother, doth not apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto the ſoules, ſéeing ſuch names
<pb facs="tcp:14860:36"/>
do not belong to them. For one ſoule doth not beget another, that it may chalenge to it ſelfe therby the name of a parent. But one man begetteth another.</p>
            <p>And furthermore this commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, thou ſhalt not commit adulterye, can not bée ſpoken, or vnderſtoode aptlye of the ſoules, ſéeing in them there is no diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſculine, or feminine kinde, or apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or deſire of carnall copulation, and where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſire is not, it is impoſſible, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mixture ſhould be made. But amongſt whom ſuch mixture is not, truely lawful copulation, namely which is in wedlocke cannot be found, &amp; where ſuch copulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as is in wedlocke, is not, there alſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull deſire of carnall companye with another mans wife (for that is adultery) hath no place.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, the precept of eſchuing theft, or deſire of too muche, doth not ſerue for the ſoules. For they haue no néede of ſuch thinges, as they that haue néede of, do get for themſelues for their naturall néede, or neceſſitie, either by thefte, or robbery, as golde, ſiluer, cattell, or any thing els ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, either for meate, or apparell.</p>
            <p>For that is vnprofitable for an immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall nature, which is deſired of them, that
<pb facs="tcp:14860:37"/>
néede, becauſe it is profitable.</p>
            <p>But let a more curiouſe trade be left for them, whiche deſire more diligentlye to ſearch out theſe thinges, or more earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſtriue with our aduerſaryes.</p>
            <p>But ſéeing thoſe things, which haue bene ſpoken before, be ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for vs, &amp; agrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with theſe things, &amp; as it were with one conſent do eſtabliſh the reſurrection, it doth not ſéeme conuenient to tary lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in them.</p>
            <p>For we did not direct our purpoſe to this marke, that wée ſhould omit nothing, that belongeth to this matter, but that wée might briefly declare to all them, that are come hyther, what men oughte to thinke concerning the reſurrection, and that by the force of thoſe things, that we haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſpoken, they mighte meaſure the force of other reaſons, belonging to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Séeing thoſe thinges, whiche wée had in hande be ſearched out, and examined, it remayneth nowe, that wée conſider the cauſe of the ende, already playne, and euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which hath néede of no care more, then that it bée added to the reſt, leſt it ſéeme either to be omitted by reaſon of obliuion, or hinder the argument in hand,
<pb facs="tcp:14860:37"/>
and diuiſion made in the beginning. For theſe cauſes, and other belonging to the ſame purpoſe, it ſhall bée conuenient, to declare the matter only for this cauſe becauſe thoſe things, whiche conſiſt by nature or arte, haue their peculiar ends, which cuſtome, &amp; common vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding doth teach, &amp; thoſe things which are before our eyes, do witneſſe the ſame.</p>
            <p>Do wée not ſée one ende ordeyned for huſbandmen, another for Phiſicions, and againe one for thoſe thinges, which growe out of the earth, another for crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures liuing therby, and ingendered ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to a naturall order, and ſequele of ſucceſſion?</p>
            <p>Wherefore, if it bée euidente, and neceſſarye, that naturall, and artificiall faculties, and the actes of them do fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe their ende, euery one according to his nature: it is neceſſarye altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the ende of man, be excepted from the communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the reſt, as a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar nature.</p>
            <p>For it is not lawful to aſſigne one end to thoſe things, which lacke reaſonable iudgement, and thoſe, which according to naturall lawe, and reaſon dooe their actions, and vſe wiſedome, and iuſtice
<pb facs="tcp:14860:38"/>
in life.</p>
            <p>Neither therfore voydneſſe of gréefe is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proper, &amp; peculiar end of theſe things. (For you maye finde that alſo in thoſe, that bee without ſenſe) nor yet the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying of thoſe thinges, whiche delight, or nouriſh the body, nor aboundance of pleaſures. Otherwiſe it were neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the beaſtly life did excell, &amp; the life adorned with vertues were an vnperfit thing. For ſuch an end is proper to bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, and cattell, &amp; doth not perteyne to men, which haue an immortall ſoule, &amp; reaſonable iudgement, nor yet the feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of the ſoule ſeparate from the body.</p>
            <p>For we do not looke vpon either the life, or end of either parte, of which man conſiſteth, but on that, whiche hath ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and perfection of both partes.</p>
            <p>For man which hath receiued this life, is ſuch a one. And it is neceſſary, that he haue a proper end, agréeable to his life.</p>
            <p>Wherfore, if an end muſt be ordeyned for that, which is both together, namely for that which conſiſteth both of ſoule &amp; body, &amp; you cannot finde it, neither while he continueth in this life, for the cauſes now oftentimes alleged, nor then, when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule is ſeparate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the body, becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:14860:38"/>
man muſt be thought no ſuch thing, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his bodye is diſſolued, or wholye diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, although the ſoule remayne by it ſelfe, it is altogether neceſſarye that the end of men do appeare in ſome other recompoſition, and renuing of both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and the ſame creature, and ſéeing that doth followe of neceſſitie, it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary alſo, that there be a reſurrection of bodyes dead, and wholye diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and that the ſame men be made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, ſéeing that the law of nature doth commaunde not euery ende, nor of all men, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of thoſe, which liued in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer life. But it is impoſſible for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame men to be made again, vnleſſe the ſame bodyes be reſtored to their ſoules. But that the bodye receyue the ſame ſoule, can by no other meane be broughte to paſſe, then by the reſurrection.</p>
            <p>For when that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to paſſe, an apt ende doth followe the nature of men, an ende trulye of: a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> life, and reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble iudgment. A man ſhall not offend if he ſaye it is it, that wée maye for euer cleaue, and continue with thoſe thinges, wherwith chiefely, and eſpecially natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reaſon doth agrée, and conſent, and that in reſpecte, and conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of him,
<pb facs="tcp:14860:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
which is, &amp; for the behoofe of thoſe things which it pleſed him to promiſe, although the common ſort of men more earneſtly, and vehemetlye deſire ſuch thinges, as are nowe preſentlye, and dooe nothing eſtéeme or regarde this ende. For the multitude of ſuche, as do leaue, and go from the ende agréeable to them, doth not wea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> common ordinaunce of duety <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> a peculiar examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pointed againſt that, and puni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ment, and rewardes or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ned, which be correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondent to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of well or euill do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:14860:39"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
